[Music]
This is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Welcome to software engineering radio.
I'm your host Gregory Caphammer. I'm
excited to introduce Samuel Kulovven.
He's our guest today as we talk about
systems like Pyantic, Pyantic AI, and
Pyantic Logfire. Samuel is the CEO and
founder of the Pyantic company, and he's
really well known in the Python
community for building a wide variety of
cool tools, three of which we're going
to dive into today. Samuel, welcome to
Software Engineering Radio.
Thanks so much for having me. Yeah,
really looking forward to our
conversation.
I'm really looking forward to the
conversation as well. So, we're going to
talk about three tools and they have
similar names. And before we dive into
the first tool, I'd like to get like a
highle understanding of what those three
tools are and maybe how they're
connected to each other and how they
might leverage each other. So, the first
question for you is what is paid? Can
you help us out?
I can. It's not always the easiest
question to answer directly. So,
Panantic to all intents and purposes is
a data validation library for Python,
but it does a bunch more stuff above and
beyond simple data validation like
controlling serialization, coercion when
you're validating and generating JSON
schema.
Okay, that's helpful. We'll dive into
more details in just a moment, but the
next quick question, what is Pyantic AI
and how is it connected to Pyantic? So,
Pyantic AI is an agent framework or a
library to interact with LLMs from
Python. It uses Pyantic and obviously
it's built by us, the same team. Pyantic
is very widely used in interactions with
LLMs in particular validating structured
outputs. So, hence we thought it was a
relevant thing for us to go and build.
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense. And
I've used other LLM frameworks and I
even noticed that they're using
paidantic. So I can imagine why it's
helpful to have the AI framework that
comes from the Pyantic team.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay. And then quickly the third
question, what is Logfire and how does
Logfire connect to the other systems
that we mentioned?
So Logfire is an observability platform.
So we do logs, traces, and metrics let
you understand, monitor your
application. It is very useful when
you're building applications in Python
in general, but particularly AI
applications. So it works nicely with
pyantic AI although we're very keen on
building on open standards. So you can
use Logfire with anything that speaks
open telemetry and you can actually use
Pantic AI with anything that will
receive open telemetry.
You mentioned a moment ago open
standards and we're going to start
talking about Pantic and some of its key
features and how you built it and
refactored it. But for our listeners who
haven't tried it yet, it's important to
note that Pyantic is an open- source
tool and they can go to GitHub and they
can try it out. they can pip install it
or UV install it and so it's really a
great framework for them to get up and
running if they've never done data
validation in Python.
Yeah, absolutely. So we're very keen on
open source and on contributing to open
source system. So Pantic is open source,
MIT licensed. Uh all of the building
blocks are obviously also MIT licensed.
Then Pantic AI is also open source and
MIT licensed. So you can go and use it.
You can even copy bits of it as certain
companies have done recently. Although
logfire the back end is closed source
because that's our commercial wing and
we think it's important to be clear
where we're being commercial versus
where we're contributing to open source
but again we're building on open
standards that we'll come to later but
even within logfire our SDKs for Python
now but for other languages coming very
soon open source and MIT licensed again
so you can use them and send the data to
the logfire back end we hope and pay us
eventually but also to anything else
that speaks open telemetry.
Sure that makes sense and that's a
helpful response. Let's talk quickly
about data validation. You mentioned it
a moment ago. Can you say in more detail
what is data validation and then maybe
give a concrete example of how a
programmer would do data validation with
pyantic?
Yeah, absolutely. I think the main thing
that I neglected to include when I first
described pyantic is that we use type
hints in Python. So type annotations
like string or int or list of integers
etc etc to define the schema that we use
for the validation. So the best way to
think about it from a high level is if
you are new to coding, your first week
of writing code, you get told that
you're going to write this computer code
and it's going to be interpreted by a
machine and so you need to be very
precise in how you define everything and
you make what seem like trivial mistakes
and then the program crashes. And yet as
you start to learn Python, you will be
shown data classes for example where you
define your fields and you add a type
annotation which says this thing is
going to be an integer, this thing is
going to be a string, this thing is
going to be a dictionary of strings
mapping to lists of sets of integers or
whatever it might be. And then you go
and initialize your data class and
actually you can use whatever type you
like. And sure, your IDE might complain
and put a little squiggly line
underneath and if you get to using a
type checker, that will complain. But
actually at runtime, you can pass
whatever types you like. And of course,
in some cases, that's easy. That's
useful as a kind of way to escape the
constraints of the language. But often
that's not helpful. You want to for
yourself be warned or error when you
pass the wrong types. But that becomes
even more important when you start to
load data that someone else has has
generated or receive data someone else
has written. So whether that be parsing
a CSV file, processing an API request,
loading data from an HTTP form,
accepting input from the terminal,
anything where you have basically the
boundaries of your application where
you're receiving data that doesn't fit
within the typing system, type hints are
basically useless because they're not
enforced at runtime. And so what Pyantic
basically does is take those type hints
and enforce them.
Okay,
but we do a bit more on top of pure
enforcement. So we will in general
although we have a strict mode where
this doesn't happen we will coersse
types where you would want to. So for
example if you have a integer field and
you pass it the string 1 2 3 pantic will
identify that that string would be valid
as an integer and coersse it to an
integer and so you will get 123 into
that field instead of an error.
Okay. So first of all, it's important to
point out like you said a moment ago
that by default type hints or type
annotations, they don't actually play
into the running of your Python program.
But if you use a tool like Pyantic, it
can run in either a strict mode or a
data coercion mode and it can help you
to validate or confirm that you're
getting the data that I expected. Is
that the right way to think about the
tool so far?
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay. But often what you find once
you've done this validation and you have
your data in Python is you will also
want to go and serialize it to another
format. So export it either marshall it
to a simple dictionary for example or
output it to JSON. And so as well as
doing the validation and indeed parsing
JSON, we will also serialize data to
JSON or to Python objects with a bunch
of control over exactly how that
happens. And then the kind of the third
bit is generating a schema for your
types. So let's say you define a pyantic
model or a data class which says we have
let's say it's a user signup form. So we
have the user's name. We have their
email address which we need to be a
valid email address. We have their date
of birth which is going to be a date
field. Then as well we can obviously do
the validation. I've said we can do the
serialization but we can also generate
JSON schema which is an open standard
that defines the fields of that form for
example and so that's useful in lots of
contexts in LLM but also in general web
development where you can use that
schema to define your form on the front
end.
Mhm. A moment ago you mentioned strict
mode versus data coercion. Can you give
a more complicated or real world example
of data coercion like in the context of
AI or a web application? Yeah,
internally we refer to strict mode
versus lax mode and the principle of
pyantic. Prior to v2 we only had what we
would now call lax mode. So it was
always coercing. Now we have that switch
across the whole of the library. But
there are lots of scenarios where often
you just can't generate the right data.
So for example, if you're receiving JSON
data, you can't have a date. So you have
to be able to take, for example, a
string and coersse it to a date object
in Python. If you're parsing URL
arguments or environment variables,
everything has to be a string. So you
can't even submit an integer. You have
to submit a string which will then need
to be coerced to an integer. So there
are lots of scenarios where we need that
coercion for things to make sense. But
there are also many scenarios where a
user gets something wrong or an LLM gets
something wrong when it's generating
data. So perhaps you submit a list when
the application wants a tupole or you
send in a set when the application wants
a frozen set or as I say you submit a
string in ISO A6001 format representing
a date rather than the date object. And
so we have fairly fine grain control
over where and when we will coersse
things to the correct type. As you can
imagine that comes with a bunch of
nuance. It's not exactly clear when you
should coers and when you shouldn't. But
we try to follow a bunch of sensible
rules and be explicit about when we will
and won't coersse. But the high level
principle which we can stick to is
whatever you define in your Python type
is this is what I want. We will
guarantee you or as far as any open
source library will ever guarantee we
will guarantee you that that's the
object you will get.
Okay. Now a moment ago you also
mentioned data serialization to JSON.
Can you briefly say what's serialization
and then how do you serialize it in
paidantic to a JSON file?
Yeah, absolutely. So serialization is
the process of going from types in the
language. So a Python dictionary, a
Python date to Python string, etc. to
some external format. Pyantic has
specific support for serializing to
JSON. So we will take the Python object
that we validated in general and we will
serialize that to JSON and we have some
control over where you can customize
that where you can for example omit none
values or omit default values or omit
specific values in general also how you
might change the serialization format
for say a date etc etc. The other bit I
missed to say is that within Pyantic V2,
we also have specific support for
parsing JSON. And that's actually very
important because you can imagine in
some scenarios in strict mode, if you
only ever validated the Python object
you got out of passing JSON, you could
never construct a date because strictly
you can't define a date in JSON. And so
if Pyantic was only able to operate on
the Python object you got from
deserializing, you could never have a
date field. And so what we're able to do
is have strict mode, but because we know
we're passing JSON, we now say that
strictly in JSON, a date must be a
ISO8601 date format, for example. And
there are many other examples. For
example, you might have a path, you
can't have a path type in JSON, and so
you would need to accept a string as the
input to that. So there's a bunch of
nuance in there, but yeah, as well as
doing the parsing of JSON, we'll also
serialize to JSON.
Okay, so that's helpful. And you've
mentioned V2 several times and we're
going to dive into V2 and how it was
rewritten in Rust and we'll talk about
all the performance improvements that
came with that. But before we do that
deep dive, can you give us like a
success story or a concrete example of a
system that actually uses Pyantic for
some kind of large scale data validation
or serialization?
Oh, there's so many examples. Some of
which I have some understanding of. So
for example, many banks. I can think of
five or six now, but I maybe maybe they
don't want me to name them will use
paidantic for validating the data they
receive from interbank transfers. So
obviously a very critical task where you
absolutely want to be sure that you're
getting the right types of data, they
will use it for that. NASA use pyantic
quite widely. For example, the services
they built to show the imagery from the
James Web Space Telescope is built on
fast API which in turn is built on
hideantic. As I say, we'll talk more
probably about the LLM specific case,
but parsing the output of structured
data. So all of the model SDKs, but also
the agent frameworks are using pideantic
for that. Yes, such a wide range of
applications, many of them proprietary
and internal. But I know for example
inside Microsoft, inside Google, in
Google Drive, there's an awful lot of
Pantic under the hood. I know inside
OpenAI, there's enormous amounts of
pideantic going on both in their
training and in their inference side.
It's all over the place because Python's
great because it is not strictly typed,
but there are so many boundaries of your
application where having that strictness
is useful.
Okay, that was a great response. So,
it's clear that we're using this kind of
system for data validation and
serialization across a wide variety of
domains, open source projects, and
different companies. And I know when I
read the documentation for Bidantic,
which is something I've been using for
years, you often say V1 and then
sometimes, and we've heard you say it
now, you say V2. So what's V1 and what's
V2 in the context of Pyantic?
Yes. So So Pyantic started off in 2017,
obviously preversion one as a completely
aside project. In I guess around 2019,
we went to V1 and we obviously became
more stable in the library. But at the
beginning of 2022, Pinatics adoption had
grown enormously. It was still a side
project for me. So I would like try to
spend an hour or so helping people in in
the evening after work, but it was
still, as I say, a side project for me.
But the internals of Pantic v1, it was
all Python. I wasn't particularly proud
of the internals. And so beginning of
2022,
I started working full-time on Pantic,
rebuilding the core in Rust. So there's
an amazing library called PIO3 that
allows you to write Python extensions in
Rust which gives you an enormous
performance improvement. But it's
actually it goes beyond simply the
performance. It allows you to write
fundamentally more robust and scalable
and maintainable code when you're
building these big performance critical
complex applications. And so I started
off on what I thought was going to be a
relatively quick project or a three or
four month project to rewrite the core
of Pyantic in Rust. That ended up taking
about a year and a half and uh I started
a company Pantic in the middle of that
process. Hired a team and it was only
because I was able to hire a team that
we were already able to complete it. But
today Pyantic V2 is like way ahead of
Pantic V1 in terms of usage and we got
somewhere between 5 and 80 times
performance improvement for validation
and serialization out of doing that
upgrade and I think it has been part of
the thing that has cemented pyantic as
kind of the default way of doing data
validation in the Python ecosystem. So,
Python v1 is a pure Python
implementation and then v2 is rewritten
in rust. There was an episode of
software engineering radio about whether
you decide to refactor or to rewrite.
You must have gone through some
interesting discussions to decide to
rewrite paidantic in v2 using rust. So,
like what were the technical challenges
that drove this rewrite and how did you
decide to rewrite versus refactor?
You said python v1. Pantic v1. Yeah, it
was pure Python and V2 uses Rust. Look,
I'd love to say that we had some like
grand vision. I was super compelled by
Rust as a way. I spent a few days
prototyping. I became convinced this was
going to give us a massive speed up. And
I kind of got building. At the time,
there was some very nice nice people,
Eric in France and Hassan who still
works with me in Germany helping me do
some maintenance, but like the vast
majority of it was me on my own. And in
terms of that decision to do the
rewrite, that was just me sort of
experimenting and going off and trying.
And like so many technical projects, it
would probably never have happened if I
had known how hard it was going to be.
It's the naivity and the curiosity of
the thing that drives projects that end
up, I think, making things much better.
But no sort of simple sit down and try
to analyze the strengths or weaknesses
or the pros and cons for this project
would have resulted in it happening. It
was a result of like I say this like
naive curiosity.
A moment ago you mentioned PIO3. Can you
tell us a little bit more about what
that is and how it helps Python
communicate with Rust?
Yes. So obviously CPython which is the
version of Python most of us use is
written in C and it has what they call
an AI which is effectively an interface
to the dynamic library that allows you
to extend Python using C. So the point
is that there are hook points into you
effectively write a DLL a binary library
in your chosen operating system and
Python knows how to look inside that and
pull out functions that it can call and
that has been used for years. So
libraries like NumPy use that
extensively to write the most
performance critical parts of the
codebase. The problem is that most of us
don't want to be writing C. It's
extremely easy to make mistakes. It's
extremely hard to be productive and the
errors that can result like memory
errors are particularly catastrophic
because your application will just crash
on the spot with sec fault or even worse
it will just go and behave in some
unexpected way but continue to
apparently behave and that's where we've
had many of the worst software bugs have
happened over the years have been a
result of those memory errors. So Rust
is a language that originally came out
of Mozilla which tries to be as
performant as C but avoid those risk of
memory errors in particular and it has
an amazing developer experience, amazing
ecosystem of libraries. It feels in many
ways like working with JavaScript or
Python but with the low-level control
and performance you would get from C.
And so PIO3 is a project that allows you
to effectively ultimately build those
same dynamic libraries but writing Rust
code instead of writing C code. And so
David Hwitt who I'm very pleased to say
I work with who works with me on
pilantic is the main maintainer of pio3
there's a bunch of other people who
contribute a lot but yeah it tries to be
a way to let you write python libraries
but in rust
okay so you can go basically from your
python programs address space to the
rust version of pyantic. So there's some
overhead you would think in terms of
Python calling Rust and it turns out to
be the case however counterintuitively
that Pyantic version two is
significantly faster than version one.
So can you maybe dive into more details?
Can you tell us why it is so much faster
than version one?
So there is very little overhead. So, so
as I say when you're writing Python code
in the end you're writing instructions
to a C program as to how to execute
right because in the end Python itself
is written in C or the main version most
of uses and so Rust effectively gives us
low-level primitives to write C
functions effectively functions that C
code can call and so there is a tiny
it's in the order of singledigit nancond
overhead to calling a pio3 function some
of that will go away eventually but rust
is somewhere depending on what you're
being 100 times faster than Python code
to execute. And so although you have
this minuscule overhead for calling the
Rust function, that is much more than
made up for by doing all of the rest of
the validation in Rust. And the point is
you get to operate with a mixture of
pointers to Python objects. So let's say
you have a Python dick that you can
interact with in Rust. You can iterate
over it. You can add members to it, etc.
But you can also, let's say you have a
string, you can have a pi string which
is a pointer to the python string
object. But you can also get out of that
a rust string object. And that allows
you to then go and operate on the
low-level of rust and operate on that
string. You can pass that string around
by reference very cheaply in a way that
Python when you pass a string to a
function, you're not passing by
reference in the same way.
Okay, that really makes sense and I'm
glad you gave those additional details.
Now, I looked on the website and I
remember you a moment ago saying a
similar number, but Pyantic V2 is either
like five times up to 50 times faster
and it's commonly about 17 times faster.
And I know you have a benchmarking
framework and you must have needed to
repeatedly run benchmarks in order to
gauge how good of a job you were doing
at the rewrite. So, can you tell us a
little bit more about your benchmarking
process? when I was working on pyantic
core which is the rust component. So
pyantic v2 is split effectively into two
libraries. We have pyantic core which is
basically the rust code and then we have
pantic itself which has pantic core as a
dependency. Pantic is responsible for
basically taking those type annotations
and turning them into what we call core
schema and then you can take a core
schema which is a relatively simple
structure of dictionaries etc which
defines a schema and then pyantic core
will take the core schema and turn that
into a schema validator and a schema
serializer which are then Python objects
which are using rust code which you can
then use to perform the validation. And
so when I was working on Pyantic core, I
spent a lot of time doing benchmarks to
try and work out where to ek out a bit
more performance where the slowdowns
were coming from. I started off using
the pi test benchmark library that had a
number of drawbacks. And so I ended up
implementing pi test speed which is for
the most part API compatible with piest
benchmark but has a few quality of life
improvements, nicer tables it will spit
out in terms of showing you those
benchmarks. Pi test speed is not heavily
maintained by us anymore, but it was
very useful at the time and I think it
still works well. But then partway
through that Arthur got in touch with me
who was looking into starting a company.
What he's built is CODspeed which is
basically a continuous benchmarking
framework. So Codspeed does two things.
One, they have a way of running your
benchmarks using Val Grind. Val grind is
a way of measuring the number of CPU
cycles that are performed when you
execute some code rather than measuring
the time which means you can run
benchmarks in a noisy environment like
GitHub actions and get reliable outputs.
And then the second thing they have is
basically a view where you can see how
benchmarks change over time and it will
literally ping up on a pull request and
say this pull request is failing because
this benchmark has got worse or lots of
green ticks if the benchmarks have got
faster. And that allows us to continue
to improve performance, but also detect
when there are regressions and go and
improvement. And even better nowadays,
if you look at Codspeed, they will give
you a flame diagram, a flame chart of
which bits of the execution are taking
what amount of time and then where the
change is coming from. So you can get
like a very nuanced description of how
the performance is changing in a given
benchmark. So it's awesome. Although
that COSE came about as we were working
on pilantic, we use it heavily on
Pyantic core and on some other
libraries. Hm, that's interesting. I
actually didn't know that there was an
integration with Val Grind, but I can
imagine that being incredibly helpful.
Yeah, it works really well because it
means we can do run the benchmarks on
CI. They get sent to Codspeed. Codspeed
then puts the comment onto the pull
request saying here are the
improvements, here are the
deteriorations, and we can be pretty
confident that we don't randomly
introduce big slowdowns. But that's only
half the work. I think we have probably
ballpark 100 different benchmarks to
measure the different performance
aspects of pantic core because there are
so many different things that you're
doing. You think it's like simply doing
validation but it can be as simple as we
have whatever it is 40 different types
that we validate and combinations of
them and serialization and we have JSON
versus Python etc etc. So I have one
more question about the rewrite and then
I want to talk a little bit further
about how people might extend Pinantic
or connect it to other tools but just
quickly as you were working on the
rewrite at what point did you feel
confident that hey this is going to pay
off and I'm definitely going to get a
system that's better than V1. From very
early on I was able to get benchmarks
that showed validating simple things
that was showing the kind of yeah 10 20x
speed up which is massive right because
it you know we talk generally about 5%
10% 20% speed ups this is 10 20x
improvement in performance which is
massive right I mean I was confident
from the beginning it was possible I
suspect probably too much so at times I
think that like I'll be honest anyone
who's worked with pantic v2 will know
that the challenge of migrating from V1
to V2 was quite big. We probably didn't
do a good enough job of reducing the
complexity of upgrading. In particular,
we as well as the rewrite in Rust. We
also fixed a bunch of APIs that we
thought were wrong from V1, but that
meant that the overhead of upgrading was
relatively large.
Okay. So, there were changes to the API
that means people have to actually write
Pantic code a little bit differently in
V2 than they do in V1.
Yeah, exactly. Well, we tried to a
certain extent to have fallback
functions for the old names and
deprecation and stuff like that, but
there were also these subtle changes
where we had basically fixed the
semantics of where we would coersse and
where we wouldn't, which are much harder
to detect from a simple like review the
code. And yeah, I know a lot of people
have had trouble with the upgrade from
V1 to V2. It's also it's made
particularly difficult in the Python
ecosystem because you can't install two
versions of a package in Rust or in
Typescript. You can install two
different versions of a package. So if
two different libraries you're using use
different versions of some third library
you can install both of those versions
in the Python ecosystem that's not the
case. So for example fast API upgraded
pretty quickly to v2 but lang chain took
much longer to upgrade to v2 and so
there was a long time when you couldn't
use the latest version of fast api and
lang chain and that caused a lot of
friction both for the library
maintainers but also for library users.
Yeah, the pain you're describing of a
Python programmer is one that I myself
have experienced many times, especially
it's more painful if you have also
programmed in Rust or JavaScript. You
mentioned fast API and I should share
with our listeners, we also had an
episode about fast API and I'll make
sure to link to that in our show notes.
What I wanted to do very quickly is talk
about ways in which you can connect
Pyantic to other types of systems. For
example, I know you can connect Pyantic
to Reddius or to a relational database
through like SQL Alchemy. So, can you
tell our listeners a little bit more
about how they can connect Pyantic to
other types of systems?
Yeah, there are lots of different
libraries for doing this, OMS in the
case of rational databases, what called
ODMs in the case of databases like
MongoDB and I guess Reddius. But the
principle comes back to the same thing I
was talking about earlier. One, you have
to do this kind of upcasting of types.
So you might not get back a data object
from say reddus. You would get back a
string and you need to do that coercion.
But you also want to make sure that what
your application is expecting in terms
of a field type matches what's actually
there in the type. And so lots and lots
of these libraries for connecting to
databases use pyantic under the hood to
perform validation and serialization in
a highly performant way. Yeah. So so you
can go and look I think the main reddest
library has integration with pantic.
There's SQL models from Sebastian, the
same person who built fast API which
built on top of SQL Alchemy and Pyantic.
Uh there's Beanie for MongoDB and a
myriad of others, not all of which I can
exactly name right now, but yeah, lots
and lots of different tools that use
Pyantic and allow you to connect to data
stores of different types. So the way
that I think about it is that if your OM
uses paidantic, you can have more
confidence in the correctness and the
reliability of your interaction with the
OM because of the fact that it's using
pyantic. Am I thinking about it the
right way?
Yeah, absolutely. And also as the
maintainer of those libraries, there's a
bunch of less work to do because you
don't have to worry about every single
time what like how am I going to do the
translation from a Postgress wire
protocol date format into a Python date
object. You can rely on pyantic to do it
correctly and if pantic is doing it
wrong, we go and fix it once in pantic
and then everyone benefits from it.
Sure, that makes a lot of sense. So
let's talk a little bit now about
pyantic AI which is another system that
you and your team are building. My
impression is that Pyantic AI helps me
as a programmer interact with LLMs. Can
you pitch for us at a high level what
does Pyantic AI do and how does it
leverage all of the things we've talked
about already?
Yeah, absolutely. So there are kind of
two sets of problems in interacting with
LLMs. One is that we all want to build
in a model agnostic way. We want to be
able to switch in and out the different
model providers very quickly or
inference providers. So none of us know
yet which model is going to be most
performant over the last year or two. As
these models have scaled up, as these
companies have scaled very quickly, they
haven't always been the most reliable in
terms of uptime. So it's very useful to
be able to switch between models for
that reason. But it's mostly about not
knowing which is best for our
application today, let alone which is
going to be best for our application
tomorrow and in a year's time. So the
number one piece of value I think that
pantic AI brings is this model
agnosticism. You can switch in and out
OpenAI, Anthropic, Gemini, Grock,
Deepseek, etc., etc., Mistral, Coher
with one line of code. But above and
beyond that, although all we're doing
fundamentally is making these API
requests and processing the responses,
the systems of interactions that people
are building, in particular, Agantic
workflows have got relatively complex
and we don't want to have to manage
every single I'm going to make this API
request here, I'm going to process the
response here. Although there is an
awful lot of unknown and an awful lot
still to be decided in terms of best
practice of using LLMs, there's a bunch
of stuff we are confident of. So for
example, lot everyone from lang chain to
crew AI to f data to small agents etc
etc all of the agent frameworks llama
index as well are using pantic to define
the schema for structured outputs
whether that be tool calls or other
forms of structured outputs. The point
being you define a pilantic model or a
data class or whatever else. Pyantic
will then go and build a JSON schema.
You then pass the JSON schema to the
model as the definition of for example
the parameters for your tool call. The
model then returns you some data that
may or may not match that schema. If it
passes, we always want to do the
coercion. So the upgrade to full Python
types because we're getting back JSON.
If that passes, great. We can then go
and call our tool or process our
structured output. But if it fails, we
then want to encode a description of the
errors, pass that back to the model, and
ask it to try again. And I think it's
fair to say now that given pyantic has
been around for a long time and has been
being used for this use case for a while
now, models are actually trained
directly on pyantic errors. And so they
do particularly well at basically taking
a pyantic error and interpreting how to
correct the data they're returning to
match the schema that they're asked to
generate. And so we generally call that
thing reflection. And that's another
thing that Pyantic AI has out of the box
that people generally want to use. But
the other bit is this loop. The general
agreement on what an agent is is
effectively a for loop where you're
asking a model to to perform an action,
looking at the structured output,
deciding what to do next, and going
around in a loop. And that's again
there's no reason why you should go and
implement that loop yourself. Why not
use pyantic AI that will go and
implement that for you? But but still
the principle is to give you the
low-level control if you want to that
allows you to decide exactly how you
want your model interactions to behave
if the defaults we give don't work well
enough or if you're doing something
esoteric enough that the default doesn't
work.
Okay. So I can use pyantic AI to give
structured content to the LLM and when
the LLM returns then I can kind of use
pideantic again in order to validate its
response. And then you talked about the
agent as being like a for loop. So it
sounds like pideantic AI also has
features for steering the interactions
with the LLM. Am I summarizing it
correctly?
Yeah, you're summarizing agent type well
and that is our primary kind of
interface for interacting with models.
We also have within the pilantic AI repo
pyantic graph which is a finite state
machine library in theory that has
nothing to do with LLM. You can use it
to go and build things that are
effectively equivalent to finite state
machines but type safe in the same way
that piantic is type safe unlike most
finite state machine libraries in
Python. That is particularly useful when
you're building the more complex
workflows where you have a complex
system of state and you want to manage
that in a in a robust way. But yeah, in
the simple case of using our agent type,
it's it's basically this this idea of a
for loop where we go and generally call
a bunch of tools until we arrive at some
answer and and then and then end.
So you mentioned state machines and
that's something that I wanted to dive
into in greater detail. Can you say
briefly what is the state machine and
then how does my Python program use the
state machine to help me build an
AIdriven application?
Yeah, so I started off as a cynic about
the state machines. I hadn't ever found
them that useful in application
development. And the main reason for
that is that most state machines are
fighting your application itself. So
although we don't think of it this way,
applications always have a state and
that state is whereabouts in the code
you're currently executing. So to give a
completely different example that I
found really interesting when I when I
identified what was wrong, we have this
JSON paraser that we use within Pyantic.
It's very fast, but it also allows us to
do iterative JSON parsing. So basically
parsing returning data as we pass the
JSON. And I when I started implementing
the JSON parser, I was like, oh, we're
going to need a state here. The state
being like I'm inside a string. I'm
after a string. I'm inside a list. And
you can imagine this might be some kind
of stack of of different states as we go
into recursive objects. And it just
wouldn't work. And it wouldn't work. And
I tried to change the different states
and I tried to diff change how the
application worked and it would nothing
was working until I realized and
obviously I was I was very concerned
about performance. So even if I got
something to work if it wasn't fast
enough that wasn't good enough. And what
I realized eventually was I didn't need
the state machine because actually the
application how it was running was the
state. If I'm in the parsing string
function I know the state I'm in. And if
I've called that from inside a list I
know that when I exit that function I'm
in the list. And so this the complex
hierarchical nested set of states that
are parsing the JSON data are
fundamentally defined by whereabouts in
my application I am not by some external
state management object. So it's very
important if you build a state machine
whether you use an existing state
machine library or you implement it
yourself that you realize
that you you need your state machine not
to fight with your application state
because that's always going to win. It
doesn't matter if I tell my application
oh I'm in state A. if I'm in the middle
of calling function B, everything it's
not going to work, right? Like the
absolute winner in terms of state is
always going to be where my application
is. And so what we wanted to do was
build a state machine library that gave
us the biggest advantages of of finite
state machines and graphs without
fighting the application itself. And so
we have this system where we use
effectively the return type just as we
use type annotations in pyantic to
define how validation is going to be
performed. We use the return type of our
node runners to define what nodes can be
called next. And so there are really
three or two advantages of state
machines. The first is that we have
effectively guard rails on how to define
our application which make it very clear
what is going on and we can get nice
things like we can get a mermaid diagram
of the actual graph of our application's
execution paths straight out of code
that is not an alternative definition.
We don't have two sources of truth. We
have our code with our type annotations
and from that we can generate a mermaid
diagram. The second is that these
complex systems don't run in one nice
Python process where they run end to
end. They are always going to be
interrupted. Whether they are
interrupted because they need to be
distributed across lots of compute or
whether they are interrupted because
they take a few seconds to run and might
be interrupted or because they might
require that the the full execution of
the graph takes weeks. So if you imagine
for example the returns process for an
e-commerce company, you can do this now.
go into Claude and ask it to give you a
complex state machine, it will print you
out a lovely mermaid diagram of the
returns process for for an e-commerce
company. And that's really neat. And if
I go and build my simple throwaway demo,
it's nice because I can be like, oh, and
now the item gets returned and I'll have
like a loading icon for 2 seconds and
now within that same process, I can go
to the like package arrives at the at
the warehouse. In reality, of course,
that's not how it works. that that
package takes a week to be returned and
I can't have the same Python process
hanging waiting for the item to be
returned and so we need this complex set
of different entry points into our
application code and that is where state
machines become so useful because you
can worry about writing your application
logic and defining your graph and
pyantic graph will take care of allowing
you to reenter that graph in any point
and what the my I think the most
compelling bit of graphs is that
whenever I've tried to build these
things myself without a graph the code
requires ired to manage re-entry in
numerous different places starts to
dominate. We end up with a spaghetti
code and the the core logic which is
often very simple gets completely
obliterated by the complexity of
re-entering the graph. And so it's this
like interruption of execution and
eliding that behind nice primitives that
is so valuable within graphs.
So it seems like at a high level we're
talking about two main approaches for
using pyantic AI. The first approach is
what you called the for loop agentic
approach and then the second approach is
the graph-based approach that uses state
machines. Can you help software
engineers decide when would they pick
one approach versus the other and then
how would they go about building and
testing it depending on the approach
they pick?
Yeah, absolutely. I mean I think it's
worth saying that they were both the
same thing ultimately. Under the hood
now our agents actually use pantic graph
to define their execution. This is
really valuable because it allows you
not only to run an agent to completion,
but you can also iterate over the
subsequent steps just as we allow you to
iterate over a graph. And similarly
within a graph, if we want to have LLM
interactions, we can call an agent from
within a node. So effectively, we have
graphs within graphs. You don't need to
think of it that way. You can be like
now I'm just going to go and call an
agent and ask it to return some
structured data and then decide what
node to call after that. But that that's
what's going on under the hood. In terms
of when should you use a graph, I'll say
now that there's a somewhat humorous and
perhaps slightly overbearing warning at
the top of our graphs documentation
saying don't use them unless you're
sure. I think that should probably be
toned down a little bit. I wrote it when
I first released graphs. I didn't want
to do what certain other library
maintainers do and basically say, oh,
you should use our most complex and
shiny thing for everything. I think
there are lots of applications that
don't need it and you should basically
be deliberate and considerate when
you're working out whether or not you
need a graph. My suspicion is which is a
really unhelpful answer you'll know when
your application is getting complex
enough that you need that graph and
you'll probably have to go and rewrite
it but you it's probably unless you know
exactly what you're doing a mistake to
start off going and using the graph. So
the analogy is basically saying graphs
are like a nail gun and lots of things
will be better solved by using a hammer.
So my suggestion would be to kind of
torture the builder analogy a bit
further. Use a hammer until you're like
this isn't working. I obviously need
something better. And then go and use
the nail gun when you're ready. And
you'll have a lot better time having
learned how to do things with a hammer.
And the problem comes when people start
with a nail gun, get carried away, and
that doesn't make them a better builder.
It makes them a builder with a nail gun.
Okay. So ultimately, the underlying
implementation is graphs and state
machines. And maybe I should start as a
developer with the simpler approach.
Ultimately, it's going to emerge that my
system is getting too complicated and
I'm trying to manage too much state on
my own. And then at that point, perhaps
I want to jump into fully learning how
to use the graph-based approach that is
built into Pyantic AI.
Yeah, that makes sense. But the other
thing I'll say is, and this is the
reason I think our nail gun warning is
too overbearing, is these graphs are not
that complicated. They're not doing
anything particularly sophisticated in
terms of your code. They're a bit more
boilerplate. we have three generics on a
graph because we're trying we're working
very hard to remain type safe. So you'll
have to deal with them. But it'll
basically mean that you have three or
four lines of code for every extra lines
of code for every function you define
which is a bit annoying if you're, you
know, it's not as elegant as just having
functions perhaps, but it's not
enormously complex. And you will see
that the actual execution of these
graphs is actually pretty simple. It's
basically call run on a on a graph node,
get back another graph node, call run on
that until we get back back an end
object and now we're finished. There's a
bunch more complexity under the hood of
state persistence which is which we
merge today and will allow you to run
graphs distributed over time or compute
but like in the end they're they're
really not that complicated to either
understand or use. Before I go to my
next question, I wanted to say I read
the overbearing warning at the top of
the documentation for the thing that
uses the state machines. And I also
smiled when I read it because it was
really a clever way of saying be
careful. You may not need this. But I
think what you're saying is that over
time it's going to be easier for
developers to just jump right in and use
that approach.
Yeah, I'm more and more compelled that
graphs are really useful in in this
space and we'll be doing a bunch more
work on them. But yeah, I think they're
really useful. Now, when you were
talking at so many different times when
you said a phrase, it made me think
like, "Oh, that's a little bit like
light LLM." Or, "Oh, that's a little bit
like lang chain." Or, "Wow, that seems a
little bit like instructor." So, I'm
wondering if you could kind of like go
through the AI LLM landscape and then
maybe make some connections between
Pidantic AI and then things like Light
LLM or Lang Chain or other tools of that
nature.
So, I'm a big fan of Instructor. Jason
who who built it is a is a friend of
mine. I think he's a bright guy and done
some interesting things. He's also been
enormously valuable to us as a company.
He gave a talk at the first AI engineer
titled Pyantic is all you need which I
think is like part of the reason that
Pyantic is now so ubiquitous in that
space. Without wanting to be rude to
people who built other libraries, I'm
not particularly impressed by any of the
other agent frameworks or libraries. the
the engineering quality is generally
much lower than you would see if you
looked at the leading Python packages
outside of the space of AI. And that is
to some extent not very surprising. The
people who have built these things are
not generally experienced open source or
Python developers. They're they're AI
experts. So we're building the thing
they need and like well done and and
that's useful of them. And we've
obviously been able in places to build
on top of what they've done in terms of
learning from from what they've done.
But none of them I think have the
engineering rigor that we would expect
of a library we would maintain or or as
I say of a library in the rest of the
Python ecosystem. We're not the only
people by a long way who built great
Python libraries. But if you go and look
at requests or httpx or rich or fast api
or numpy or pandas or a whole host of
other well-known Python libraries, go
and look through the you know python top
most downloaded 100 Python packages and
there's amazingly high quality of
engineering in most of those libraries.
And yet you switch over to LLMs and
maybe this is what happens always when
you have a kind of new space where
people are innovating quickly but the
engineering quality is just not there.
If you go and look at test coverage, if
you look at type safety, if you look at
even using linting, even testing on all
recent Python versions, there's a agent
framework not one of the ones you've
you've named that was released last year
by a relatively well-known person in the
ecosystem and it had something like 25
tests. It didn't have linting. It didn't
have type checking. Didn't even have
proper documentation. These things are
built in cases by opportunists and the
quality is not that high. And so what we
wanted to go and do was build an Asian
framework or an LLM library that
prioritized good engineering quality and
doing things properly over necessarily
implementing the latest hype cycle or
fad as fast as possible. build the I
mean I say the Django but the Django or
the first API of of the LLM space the
kind of dependable workhorse that's
going to do things properly even if
we're not jumping on necessarily the
next hype cycle immediately
okay I see what you're getting at and
I've actually run the regression test
suite for a lot of the top 100 projects
that you're talking about and I've
looked at their CI setups so I know
exactly what you're getting at when you
talk about the very high engineering
standard associated with a lot of
projects that are in the Python
ecosystem. So just really quickly before
we move on to the next topic, you
mentioned kind of the hype cycle and
perhaps I'm now using some hype cycle
phrases, but can you do things like
retrieval augmented generation when you
are using pyantic AI and maybe could you
give us an example of how you do that if
it's possible?
Yeah, absolutely. So we allow you to
implement tools of course we I think we
have the basically the best interface
for defining tools. I think that is
relatively well demonstrated by how
people are now using what we've done and
basically duplicating or copying it in
places or or just relying on pyantic AI
and the rate of adoption of pyantic AI
in terms of downloads has been
astonishing but within a tool you can
then go and call a database to search
for an embedding for example perfectly
easily that will work very well generate
the embedding and and search for the
embedding we allow most of those things
we allow you to do the more complex
things like react chain of thought that
will all work with impanski. We all have
all the primitives for those things. We
just think that it's more important to
get the typing correct, get the library
to be well tested and have good
primitives than to have necessarily have
the example of all of those things.
So, I'm going to ask this next question
in perhaps a slightly strange way, but
suppose I don't use pyantic AI and I
simply go to the documentation for
Claude and I see that there is a way for
me to write a Python program that can
interact with their LLM. What would go
wrong for me if I didn't use Pyantic AI?
I've been a little bit rude on this
podcast about some of the other agent
frameworks, but I I think generally that
the quality of the SDKs from the
inference providers is very high and
that's partly because they've been built
by companies who specialize in doing
that. So Stainless and Speak Easy have
done an amazing job of building the SDK.
So Anthropic SDK, OpenAI SDK, Grock SDK,
Mistral SDK. And so those libraries are
good in general. The two big downsides
of using them directly. one, you don't
have the option to switch out to another
model that easily. Two, there's a bunch
of stuff that you just have to go and
implement yourself. It's a bit like if
you were to go and implement HTTP
parsing by starting off with a socket
connection and saying, "I'm going to
pass the headers directly." Cool. That's
a fun thing to do. It's probably a
useful thing to do in learning how HTTP
works, but it's not something you want
to do if you're trying to build an
application. So if you wanted to for
example take a pilantic model use a JSON
schema to define my tool parameters then
validate the response and make another
call to the model if response was
invalid that is something that is that's
a pain to do manually and you would much
rather just go and you know use panti to
do it for you unless you think you are
going to the IP of what you're building
is in how you implement that in which
case you know you're totally within your
rights to go and like use the one of
their SDKs or even make HTTP requests
directly. So, when I've built Python
applications that are interacting with
cloud-based LLMs, one of the things I
often want to be able to do is save the
history of my interaction with the LLM.
Like, I want to know exactly what did I
send it, what did it come back with, how
close was that to what I was really
hoping for, and then I want to keep all
of that state as my program is running.
So I'm wondering if you can talk a
little bit about the interplay between
logging and LLMs as we transition our
conversation to a discussion of pyantic
logfire.
Yeah, absolutely. I think there's two
points you're making there. One, we
often want to store the messages to
reuse them to continue a conversation.
We want to when we make the next request
to the LLM, we want to include the
message thread such that the LLM
effectively has the context because
obviously if you just make two
consecutive requests to let's say chat
GPT without including the previous
messages, it doesn't have any context on
what you just said. So it's almost like
start a conversation with someone where
all they hear is you saying that's
interesting. Why do you think that? And
obviously they can't answer because they
don't know what it was they said before.
There's a slight subtlety there that the
new responses API from OpenAI now allows
you to basically store that thread
within OpenAI. That has some advantages.
It also has disadvantages in terms of
model agnosticism, but but whatever. So,
so the first thing we do and one of the
other like added values of using
padantic AI is we record this sequence
of messages. They automatically get
returned to the LLM if you're within the
for loop that I talked about. But you
could also record them however you want
to record them and then reuse them if
you're going to re-enter a conversation
from another point in your application.
But then the other bit that you're
talking about is basically being able to
see the messages exchanged with a model
for observability reasons. So for or
eval to try and work out what the hell
my application is doing, what the model
is doing and ultimately go about
improving it or identifying if it's
behaving badly and you know stop that.
And so that's an incredibly useful thing
to do. It's something that there are
emerging open standards on how to do it.
Open telemetry has a sig special
interest group working on semantic
conventions for for LLMs and we're part
of that. We were I was on the call
yesterday working out how we persist
those messages but paid already has open
telemetry integration so you can send
the data to any open telemetry compliant
platform. Obviously, we think logfire is
best, but we think that engineers are
bright enough to realize that lockin is
not a good thing and to avoid it. And
so, we're not trying to make you use our
thing through lockin. We're trying to
make you use our thing through it being
so good that you want to.
So, you mentioned a moment ago open
telemetry. And as we start talking about
logfire, the system you mentioned a
moment ago, I'm wondering if you could
say briefly what is the open telemetry
standard and why do logging systems like
your system decide to adhere to that
standard?
Yes. So open telemetry is a standard for
communicating observability data, logs,
traces and metrics. And then it is also
a bunch of SDKs for every popular
language that allow you to generate that
data and send it to an open telemetry
back end. We are doing something
slightly differently. We have uh logfire
which is our SDK for logfire which
basically is an opinionated wrapper
around open telemetry. So it makes it
more pythonic, easier to go and
effectively generate those logs and or
traces or metrics and and send them off
to an open telemetry back end. And
obviously we log fire defaults to
sending it to ours, but you can send it
to anyone you like. But yeah, open
telemetry is is an evolving standard
started off the first inklings of it
were were some projects in around 2016,
but it's really reached fruition in the
last two or three years. One of the
interesting questions is like why would
the likes of data dogs the big
incumbents allow open telemetry to
happen and indeed go and contribute to
it and although it's not particularly
clear my assumption is that the very
biggest organizations Apple and the US
government for example said if we're
going to use your thing we have to be
able to use an open standard because if
we're going to integrate this SDK all
over our applications we need to be able
to go and switch out where that data
goes because otherwise we're just like
too strongly tied into your solution. So
that's my guess about why it's come
about fundamentally. It's not perfect
like all of these open standards that
are designed by committee but I think
all things considered it's pretty
powerful. So it can send data over
either JSON or protobuff to HTTP or gRPC
backends and it's a pretty good
description of what you might want to do
in in observability. And so on top of
the fundamental protocol they have these
semantic conventions. So basically the
names of fields for things like the SQL
query or HTTP headers or LLM
interactions. And so that's what we're
talking about here.
So if listeners are interested, we have
a software engineering radio episode
that is specifically about open
telemetry and we have a number of
episodes that are about logging and
things of that nature and I'll link to
those in the show notes. What I wanted
to do now was to like read a quotation
to you that directly comes from the
Logfire documentation. So it says
automatically instruments your code for
minimal manual effort. Can you briefly
say what does it mean to instrument my
code and how does that help me as a
programmer?
Yeah. So there are two parts to that.
One is that there are existing open
telemetry integrations and some that we
have built ourselves that mean we can go
and hook into many popular libraries
you're going to go and use and
automatically effectively get data out
of them. So whether it be a web server
like fast API or Django or Flask,
whether it be a database connector like
SQL alchemy or async pg, psychoppg,
reddus etc. you can go and instrument
them httpx requests etc. You can go and
instrument them and automatically
whenever you receive an HTTP request or
make a database request or make an
outgoing HTTP request, you will get the
information about that. how long it
took, why it went wrong, if it went
wrong, details like the the status code,
the request method, the path, the SQL
query, whatever it might be, you
automatically get that. And so what we
generally see is with roughly five lines
of code, 5 to 10 lines of code, you get
80% of the value of instrumenting your
application. And you can also integrate
logfire into standard library logging.
So we if you have logs in your
application code or even in third party
libraries, they can come into logfire as
well. And so without polluting your
codebase with lots of logfire calls, you
get like 80% of the value with those
like 5 to 10 lines of code. And the same
applies to OpenAI SDK or to Pantic AI or
to the new agents SDK from OpenAI. So
that's but then the other bit of auto
instrumentation is a very clever thing
that Alex built in our team where
basically at import time of a module we
edit the a to insert traces into
function calls that take more than a
certain period of time. So we basically
get something more like profiling within
your application as it runs which is an
amazing piece of work from Alex very
useful but generally not required in
most applications but super useful if
you're like what's slow in this module
you can go and say auto instrument say I
only want to instrument function calls
that are longer than 10 milliseconds and
and it'll go and do that for you. So
that's really interesting and I didn't
know that's how it works. But basically
what you're saying is at runtime for
code that is somehow slow or likely to
be slow, you instrument the code in the
a level and then it will do all of the
logging for me and I didn't have to put
the instrumentation into the framework
that might be the slow part of my
application. Did I say that the right
way?
Roughly. Yes. Yes.
Okay. So that's really cool because
you're actually changing the abstract
syntax tree of the program at the point
when I load the code at runtime.
Yeah, exactly. That's the sort of thing
that we are able to do because we have
our own SDK where if you're using
standard open telemetry, not only do you
have these like 50 to 100 lines of
boiler plate to set up open telemetry,
but you don't get things like that. We
also have this like neat interface for
doing logging and tracing. So
logfire.info, logfire.span where we you
can send through keyword arguments, they
will become attributes. will show them
nicely in the logfire UI. Alex has
another neat bit of code where we will
go and if you use an fstring instead of
having effectively a normal string
template and then variables as you would
with logging, we will go and extract the
values from inside an string and and
show them as well.
Wow, that's cool. I would find that
helpful. So if I'm writing something
that uses fast API or HTTPX, what I'm
understanding is that you basically
already have an integration for fast API
which makes it then really easy for me
to use logfire as my logging system.
It's tracing technically but yes you
most people think of it as logging but
you'll do import logfire
logfire.configure then you do logfire
instrument fast API logfire instrument
httpx logfire instrument whatever the
package might be. we have I don't know
10 or 20 different packages available
automatically there and that's all you
need to do to then start getting in the
case of fast API like I say the HTTP
request information in the case of a
database connector the SQL queries and
how long they're taking so I don't want
my question to sound silly but many of
us are used to writing to like a
rotating log or like there's some socket
that we're listening on in order to
capture the logging information my
question is where does all the logging
information go when you're using logfire
So when you're using logfire by default
running logfire and this is actually
just we're just using the standard open
telemetry SDK for this in the
background. So it's like very battle
tested very low overhead we're running a
separate thread where we're sending data
about each individual log statement. So
that might be as simple as the the
message, but also things like timing on
a request, but also you could log
something like a pilantic model or a
data class or a datetime or even a data
frame and we'll send enough information
about that to go and recreate the rep
review of that in Logfire. That gets
sent to the separate thread. From there
it is sent over HTTP to whatever open
telemetry back end you're using. Logire
being the easiest one and the best one.
And then in Log's live view, you can
then see that log line come in. You can
see all the data about it. You can see
how long a function took to call or
whatever it might be. And you see that
in a in a like in a trace which is
basically a nested log of everything
that happened within say a function call
or a HTTP endpoint.
So many Python programmers are probably
most familiar with the built-in logging
package. Can you say one or two things
about how Logfire is different than that
built-in package?
Yes. So, as I said, we have a few neat
things like we're we're using fringing
style strings and we're we'll even
interpret the values from inside frings.
But the real power comes from
logfire.span or the the decorator
logfire. Which is the same thing which
allows us not only to have this like
linear list of events that happened, but
we have this tree structure of logs and
where within what other log, let's call
it, it's technically a span or a trace
where things happened. So instead of
having this linear list of events and it
not being trivial to work out what
happened where, we get this like tree
view of everything that happened within
your application that both matches your
mental idea of how your application
runs, but also just gives you far higher
fidelity on on what's going on.
Yeah, I see what you're saying because
essentially when I'm using the logging
package built into Python, I essentially
have to put all of the logging
statements in the right spot myself in
order to build up that understanding.
Whereas Logfire is doing a lot of that
automatically for me through the
automated instrumentation.
Yeah, exactly. But both through the
automated instrumentation and through
this system of spans and traces. So if I
do with logfire.span
start my function and then inside that I
do another logfire.info or another
logfire.span that all comes through as a
nested structure that I can see in
logfire's live view and I can understand
what my application is doing. That use
of of tracing it feels like logs but
that use of tracing is the thing that
like fundamentally is the game changer.
So, this has been both a fascinating and
fun conversation. And I know we could
have talked quite a bit more about any
one of the three frameworks that we've
discussed. But as we draw our
conversation to a conclusion, I guess I
have two main questions for you. Number
one, as you've been building all of the
tools, Pyantic and Pyantic AI and then
also the Logfire system. Is there some
lesson that you have learned about
building and maintaining top quality
frameworks?
Yeah, I I think there is enormous value
in following open standards. So, for
example, following open telemetry, sure,
it has some some limitations, but it's
enormous amount easier for us developing
because we just know what standard we're
going against. We don't have to go and
build that. But also, it's incredibly
valuable for users who know that they're
not going to be locked into logfire. So,
they can use us with confidence. Same,
we haven't talked about our database in
Logfire, which is incredibly powerful.
Allows you to write raw SQL to go and
query your data. We haven't gone and
built a database from scratch. We've
gone and collaborated with data fusion,
which is an Apache project. We talk to
the maintainers once a month why we like
have given them shares in the company
bluntly as in we've we've gone and
allowed them to like share in our
success and we find that to be a much
better way of of building than to go and
build things ourselves. So whether it be
open standards or existing projects same
as like pyantic using type annotations
as the definition of the schema. Sure it
has some limitations. Python's type
system isn't perfect but it is way more
powerful for users and way easier for us
that we know what the source of truth is
in terms of the standard. Yeah, that
makes sense. And instead of going out
and building your own bespoke type
system, you're leveraging what exists in
Python, which means you're going to get
way greater adoption than you would
otherwise.
Yeah.
So, the last question essentially has
two parts. And the first part is like,
do you have a call to action for our
listeners of Software Engineering Radio?
And then finally, is there anything that
we've overlooked that you wanted to
briefly highlight? In terms of what
we've overlooked, we have some really
exciting announcements coming up over
the the next couple of weeks, which I
presume will be out by the time this
this podcast is released. So, I would
have a look at at we'll have a blog post
up summarizing I think we have we're
calling it rolling thunder. We have
eight big announcements coming up over
the next eight business days. So, I
would really encourage you to go and
have a look at look at them on either on
Twitter or on our LinkedIn or on our
website and like those will be really
exciting. Obviously, the main call to
action is I'd love people to go and try
logfire. give us feedback. Same with
Pantic AI. You can join our Slack. You
can ask questions. It will be me or the
others maintaining the project who will
answer. And I'd love to hear people's
feedback, good, bad, or indifferent.
We're always interested in how people
are using these things. And then the
final point, I can give a kind of sneak
peek. The first of those announcements
is that we're hiring a bunch more roles
next week. So, if you're interested in
working with us, hopefully not all those
roles are filled by the time this
podcast goes out. And yeah, go and have
a look and and see if any of them
interest you.
Thanks for all those details. This has
really been a fun conversation where
we've done a deep dive into three
frameworks. If listeners are interested,
there's a whole bunch of other shows
that we have published on software
engineering radio. They're connected to
the topics for today and I'll make sure
to link to those in the show notes.
Thank you so much for being here on
software engineering radio today. It was
a lot of fun to chat with you. Really
enjoyed it. Thank you so much.
Thank you Samuel. Bye now.
Bye-bye.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.